<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>aflashyrhetoric</title>
    <link>http://kevinoh.me/categories/misc/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on aflashyrhetoric</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016 Kevin Oh</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://kevinoh.me/categories/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thresholds</title>
      <link>http://kevinoh.me/posts/Thresholds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kevinoh.me/posts/Thresholds/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;optimization-past-the-adequacy-threshold&#34;&gt;Optimization past the Adequacy Threshold&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dry-theoretical-writing-not-meant-for-consumption-by-cool-people&#34;&gt;Dry theoretical writing not meant for consumption by cool people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any given time, an entity may be in one of two states: unstable, and stable. Similarly, they may be undergoing one of three processes: repair, maintenance, and optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repair&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the processes involved with moving from an unstable state to a stable state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the processes involved with &lt;em&gt;staying&lt;/em&gt; at a stable state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimization&lt;/strong&gt;, refers to the processes involved with further improving upon the &lt;code&gt;stable&lt;/code&gt; state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us assume that all three processes exist in a continuum. Logic and reason and science equips us with the tools necessary to move from each stage to the next. However, an interesting quirk: the &lt;code&gt;Optimization&lt;/code&gt; stage has no upper limit with non-trivial entities. You could almost endlessly optimize a car until it runs efficiently from one drop of oil instead of two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And indeed, this is a measurable gain, and may be worth pursuing. But note: even at scale, this optimization would yield a savings of a few gallons of oil. I ask: if the engineer working on such a project does so while his peers suffer - is his focus defensible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repair is very often assumed to be necessary. If some necessary thing is broken, it must be repaired. And once repaired, it must be maintained such that it won&amp;rsquo;t again fall into disrepair. And once stable, it may be further improved, if such improvements are great enough to warrant the work required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But past a certain point, there is a point of diminishing return. And while such work is still &amp;ldquo;good,&amp;rdquo; it must be remembered that this work is not as important - by definition - as the work of repair and the work of maintenance and the work of valuable optimization. To this end, we might say that the phase of &lt;code&gt;Optimization&lt;/code&gt; may be split into three more sub-phases: &lt;code&gt;Practical Optimization&lt;/code&gt; vs &lt;code&gt;Impractical Optimization&lt;/code&gt; vs &lt;code&gt;Academic Optimization&lt;/code&gt;. The difference among the three: their yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s use an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine that a man has an injured ankle. &lt;code&gt;Repair&lt;/code&gt; describes the initial healing process. &lt;code&gt;Maintenance&lt;/code&gt; describes the man&amp;rsquo;s stay in a hospital, a precautionary measure to ensure that he does not hurt his ankle once more. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that the &lt;code&gt;Repair&lt;/code&gt; phase has completed and he is now &lt;strong&gt;Stable.&lt;/strong&gt; He is back to where he is. He can walk, but neither better nor worse than he could before. Optimization would be equipping him with a vehicle of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practical optimization would be giving this man a car.
Impractical optimization would be giving him a sports car instead of a sedan, because the difference between &lt;code&gt;NO CAR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CAR&lt;/code&gt; is significantly larger than &lt;code&gt;CAR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;FASTER CAR.&lt;/code&gt; An academic optimization would be giving him the latest Tesla, with optimal gas efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three are valid and important. To say prematurely that an engineer working in the field of academic optimization is somehow morally misled is, itself, morally misled and short-sighted. But I believe a criticism of that engineer&amp;rsquo;s priorities is full-warranted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And indeed, when pursuits of &lt;code&gt;Academic Optimization&lt;/code&gt; are prioritized equally with pursuits of &lt;code&gt;Repair&lt;/code&gt;, problems, anger, discomfort, and even moral indignation arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the engineer from before: an engineer tasked with making a vehicle run from one drop instead of two. Drop him in an army hospital - nurses running to and fro, weary doctors hunched over in concentration, the sounds of warfare rumbling in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is he somehow &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;? Is his existence, the volume of his life&amp;rsquo;s work - &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;? Of course not. But if, when shown a bleeding man and asked for his assistance, the engineer scoffs and says, &amp;ldquo;this work is beneath me.&amp;rdquo; That is reprehensible. If the leader of the army hospital decides that the funding toward purchasing medical supplies is to be halved, such that the engineer could finish his work instead, that is reprehensible. It is wrong not because of some arcane moral principle or tome, but because certain priorities are human - the preservation of life, the protection of peers - and to violate this hierarchy of needs for the sake of pride, image, or whatever else, that is despicable. To reject this foundational hierarchy in any serious manner is naive or foolish (or revolutionary, but I am cynical that a convincing counter-argument could be made.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s consider two more provisions of the earlier example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First. If the same engineer were to shield himself from such criticism by claiming that he is doing the same genre of work as Henry Ford, that is again despicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second. Consider a final, extreme case now - a case that here may sound bizarre but in real life is no uncommon sight: if the same engineer were so convinced of the superiority of his craft (to the doctor&amp;rsquo;s), that he went out of his way to spit on, chastise, or otherwise condemn the doctor, then that is the foulest of actions and it is despicable. If he believed that because of the &amp;ldquo;academic&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;high-order&amp;rdquo; nature of his own field, the field of the doctor&amp;rsquo;s is somehow inferior, that is arrogance and it is despicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frustrating element of it all: often, these engineers are well-meaning. They are convinced, and are just as shocked by your criticisms as you are by their arrogance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, then to resolve this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;/afr&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>